The basis of what I was saying was,
我所说的
it’s built upon the concept of perspective.
在于角度、见解
[Socrates, Castro and the King of India]
苏格拉底、卡斯特罗和印度国王
When Freud was asked,
有人问弗洛伊德
“What is the purpose of psychoanalysis?”
“精神分析法的目的是什么？”
He said— and remember, “psycho” means “soul”,
别忘了，“精神”还指“灵魂”
so we can say “soul analysis”—
所以可以称“灵魂分析”
and he said, “To convert neurotic suffering
他回答，“将神经性痛苦转换为普通痛苦”
People thought he was going to say,
人们以为他会说
“To make people happy, that’s the purpose.
“目的是让人们开心
When you undergo this type of analysis,
经过这种分析后
you’ll come out a happy person.”
你将成为一个开心的人。”
That’s what they thought, but that’s not what he said,
那是大家的想法，但不是他的
he said, “Oh, to convert neurotic suffering into ordinary suffering.”
他说，“将神经性折磨减轻为普通折磨”
It’s a little bit of a clever repartee,
这个应对很机敏
but there’s something to be said about that.
但究其背后
So what I was suggesting, by observation,
对此，我的建议是
we see: the cause of the suffering of Vraja-gopīs
我们看到那些牧牛姑娘们还有其它人的痛苦
as given in the Gopī-gītā,
《牧牛女之歌》里写道
those ślokas, “Tava kathāmṛtaḿ tapta-jīvanaḿ” etc. [SB: 10.31.9]
（梵文）
Then we hear in the Bhāgavatam,
《圣典薄伽瓦谭》里也有
Here we want to say “forgetfulness”,
我们认为是“遗忘”
but the cause is separation.
但原因是“分离”
I’m applying it to this also, and saying
在这里也可以这么说
that the real cause of our present suffering
我们目前痛苦的真正原因
is separation from Kṛṣṇa.
是与奎师那的分离
But this is one type, that’s another type,
但类别程度不同
so both can be a starting point.
但不同的痛苦都可以是个起点
So, when we read in the Gītā
在《薄伽梵歌》里读到
—but it’s qualified by the word sukṛti— it’s saying,
—前提是有sukrti福报—
people in different types of distressed conditions
人们陷入不同类型的痛苦之中
(I’ll say it that way for the sake of this talk),
（我这么说，单纯是为了这个讨论）
if they have the sukṛti— it doesn’t say everybody,
如果他们有sukrti福报，没说所有人都有
but it says, janāḥ sukṛtino ’rjuna [Bg: 7.16],
（梵文）
those who have sufficient sukṛti,
那些福报够的人
when they’re in these circumstances,
在遇到这些痛苦时
it may be a catalyst for coming in connection, spiritual search.
可能会促使他们开始灵性问询
Not everybody.
不是所有人都会
Everyone is suffering in different ways,
大家都在受苦，形式不同
but why is it, one person ...?
但为什么有人就会
Like Prabhupād says in one place, when someone
一次帕布帕德说
is a constant source of perplexity, bewilderment,
它永远让人迷惑不解，困扰焦虑
But not everybody does that.
但并不是所有人都这么做了
So the key word there is sukṛti.
关键在于sukrti福报
Those of sufficient sukṛti,
那些有足够福报的人
when they find themselves in some completely
当他们痛不欲生折磨不堪时
Vedavyās’s depression led him to dive deep into Reality.
维亚萨的抑郁促使他向本真走的更深
Of course, that’s a high example, Vedavyās.
当然举圣人维亚萨的例子过高
But someone within this world: it may,
但这个世上的人也是可能去追寻的
but it may be temporary also.
虽然有些人可能是暂时的
We hear of śmaśāna vairāgya:
就像śmaśāna vairāgya
the renunciation at the funeral pyre.
在火葬当时产生弃绝想法
People go to a funeral, and momentarily they’re thinking,
人们去参加葬礼，会突然思考
I heard some news today, some horrible news we hear
或者今天听新闻说，太恐怖了
about some children dying somewhere, or some other people,
孩童们或其他人死于非命
and then we may think, “What is this world? It’s so brutal.”
然后我们开始想了
saying, “It’s not a place fit for gentlemen”,
“这里不适合绅士”
and these different feelings may come to us.
我们会有不同的感受
But then they leave easily, also.
但转身就消失了
So, again in the Gītā Kṛṣṇa’s saying,
在梵歌里奎师那说，
janma-mṛtyu-jarā-vyādhi- duḥkha-doṣānudarśanam [Bg: 13.9],
（梵文）
if you’ve got the right darshan, perspective,
如果有正确的视角，darshan
of where you are in the world,
知道这个世界是什么样的地方
then you’ll realise that suffering, birth, death, old age, and disease,
那你就会明白这些痛苦生老病死
these are things that are inescapable,
都是无法躲避
and you’re gonna have to deal with them
必须要面对的
whether you’re in Kṛṣṇa consciousness or not.
无论你有没有奎师那觉知
As Guru Mahārāj defined “śūdra”,
Guru Maharaj定义“sudra”
in relation to the Rāmachandra pastime of beheading śūdraka,
联系到主罗摩当时斩首Sudraka
he said, “’Śūdra’, by definition, means ‘one who wails or laments’.”
他说，sudra的定义是那些恸哭哀伤的人
That’s what it literally means.
这是字面意思
Śūdra, ‘who’s crying out in agony, anxiety, wailing, lamenting’.
sudra,一个痛苦的焦虑的恸哭着的人
Why?
为什么？
Guru Mahārāj, his explanation was, he said,
Guru Maharaj解释说，
“One who accepts this life as all in all,
“认定这一生就是全部
this world as all in all,
这个世界就是全部的人
he will have to lament.”
他只能哀伤了。”
That’s why Śukadev— again, very strong language—
因此Sukadev用很强烈的措辞
is telling Parīkṣit Mahārāj near the end of the Bhāgavatam,
告诉Pariksit Maharaj
tvaḿ tu rājan mariṣyeti paśu-buddhim imāḿ jahi [SB: 12.5.2]
(梵文)
I mean it almost sounds insulting,
这话听起来有些侮辱
he’s saying, “To think that you will die is paśu-buddhi.
他说，“认为你会死，这是动物思维pasu-buddhi
Animals think they will die.”
动物才会认为他们会死。”
He’s saying, a spiritually realised advanced person,
他意思是，一个灵性觉悟的进步人士
he won’t think like that.
是不会这样想的
Dhīras tatra na muhyati [Bg: 2.13]— he won’t be bewildered by this.
他不会被此迷惑
Socrates, “Bring the Hemlock! Big glass!”
苏格拉底说，“拿毒药来！大杯的！”
Saying that, “My body will be finished,
“我的肉体会死亡，但我不会。”
but I won’t be.” He knew that.
他明白
Fidel Castro wrote some letters in the 1950s
菲德尔·卡斯特罗（古巴革命领导人）五零年时写了些信
—they discovered these kind of like spiritual letters he wrote—
—后来发现这些信很有灵性—
and, I’m paraphrasing, but he practically said,
我是在转述，基本上他说
“Once you realise that you’re not your material body,
“一旦意识到你不是这具物质躯体
but that you’re a spiritual being,
而是灵性存在
you’re not afraid of dying for the revolution, etc.”
那你将不再惧怕为了革命而丧生等等。”
Even he could understand that, on some level.
他都能明白，在一定程度上
Socrates, Fidel Castro.
苏格拉底，卡斯特罗
That’s why Mahāprabhu was telling Sanātan,
所以玛哈帕布告诉Sanatan
“To offer your body? That won’t get you Kṛṣṇa.”
"献出你的身躯？并不会让你获得奎师那"